<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An halfe-penny-worth of vvit, in a penny-worth of paper. Or, The hermites tale</title>
            <author>King, Humphrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109260</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 802:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An halfe-penny-worth of vvit, in a penny-worth of paper. Or, The hermites tale</title>
                  <author>King, Humphrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Thorp, by the assignement of Edw: Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Humphrey King.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The hermites tale.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:1"/>
            <p>AN Halfe-penny-worth of Wit, in a Penny-worth of Paper. OR,
<hi>The Hermites Tale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Impreſsion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Thorp,</hi> by the
Aſſignement of <hi>Edw: Blount.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Counteſſe of Suſſex.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N times of former ages (honourable faire La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) I haue often
heard, that Vſury, Lying, and Flattery, were worſe excommunicate out of
Court and Common-wealth, then thred-bare cloakes or greaſie bootes out of the
Preſence. O they were vertuous men in thoſe daies, &amp; would giue the
deuill his due, if it were but in wearing deuils breeches. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am growne
into ſuch infinite amours of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt packe-ſtaffe plaineneſſe,
that ſincerely and verily, I do meane, as it were, to imitate it. Firſt,
for Vſury, I hate it worſe then any empty purſe, and you ſhal haue none
of mee, I beſeech God to inſpire mee but with halfe ſo many good wordes,
as may counteruaile the hundreth part of the principal of your gracious fauors
towards me. Next for lying, in no line of this Booke ſhall you find me
lyable, (if I be not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned for too much ſpeaking the troth, I care not)
and to make you know, that I am old <hi>Tom-tel-troth</hi> indeed, I will giue
you a taſt whereby you may iudge of the reſt. <hi>Item.</hi> I ſay I am
no Scholler, if that be a lie I referre me to the iudgement of the learned, who
if they but poſe me in the petigree of a <hi>Noune</hi> and
<hi>Pronoune,</hi> I ſtraight croſſe and bleſſe my ſelfe, &amp;
thinke they begin to coniure. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I affirme that thus being no Scholler,
but a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple honeſt Dunce, as I am, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſay <hi>B</hi> to a
<hi>Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9765:3"/>it is very preſumptuouſly done of me, to
offer to hey-paſſe and repaſſe it in Print ſo, when my Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
ſcarſe euer heard of a Pen &amp; Inke-horne, &amp; much more
preſumptuouſly, it being ſuch a courſe home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpun linſey woolſey
webbe of wit as it is, to ſhroude it vnder the protection of ſo high a
perſonage, who are more worthy to patronize the deuine Muſe of
<hi>Apollo,</hi> or the thundring ſpirit of <hi>Homer,</hi> then this
Countrey dance of the worlds end, or harſh Lancaſhire Horne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe. Taxe me
who dare, or who can, that herein my tongue doubles one ſillable. Marry
ſome excuſe wold do well, for this my Eagle-ſoaring, and too too
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward attempting, and yet I need not neither, for out of your owne
ſuper-abounding good nature you would ſupply it though I let it alone;
&amp; yet I will not let it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but throw ſome light vaile, of
ſpotleſſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wel-meaning, ouer it, to huke &amp; mask it from
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ſhame &amp; obloquy: Faith, no more but this, I ſee my inferiours
in the gifts of learning, wiſedome, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, torment the
<hi>Print</hi> daily with lighter tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles and <hi>Iiggalorums,</hi> then my
ruſſet <hi>Hermit</hi> is, which hath made me the bolder to ſhoulder in
amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They clap a paire of French ſpurres on the heeles of Vice to
rowell ope the wombe of that reſty Iade Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, &amp; let all the
loath-ſome guts &amp; garbidge of his panch iſſue out to putrifie and
infect the freſh aire of <hi>Pauls Church-yard;</hi> I curbe ſin with a
double ſnaffle of reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; turne &amp; wind him with my ſmart
wand of correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to what vertuous manage I pleaſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<pb facs="tcp:9765:3"/>for my good meaning, not Art, am I to bee ſeene &amp; allowed. For my
inſolence in preſenting this home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bundle of Hermits wands to ſo
ſacred a Madam, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this couert barron it ſhall march, that weak
houſes require the ſtrongeſt props, and the poore muſt pay their fines
to their Lord or Lady whatſoeuer, be it but in pepper-cornes, or ſingle
halfe-pence. My Booke I entitle, <hi>A halfe-peny worth of wit in a peny-worth
of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> whereby it drawes ſomewhat nere to the matter &amp; the
purpoſe. If you accept it well, there is no man that will accept it ill, and
except you ſtray from the worlds ordinary cuſtome (that take Vintners
leaden halfe-pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tokens for ſound payment) you cannot accept of it
amiſſe. Imagine this one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for either it will paſſe for a
half-peny or nothing. But ſoft I haue let paſſe my laſt relique of
antiquity, which is there horrible and terrible deteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of flattery,
&amp; my religious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therunto. I haue proued my ſelfe guiltles of
lying &amp; vſury, &amp; if my Book will not ſaue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
for flatery, I wold it were treaſon to write &amp; read, or <hi>Gal,
Gum,</hi> &amp; <hi>Copperis</hi> wherof Inke is made, were held more odious
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: all the flattery that I wil vſe (if it be flattery to ſpeak
truth) ſhal be to pronounce that you are truly vertuous, faire, wiſe, &amp;
honorable: &amp; ſo I leaue you, deſiring pardon for my boldnes, and
pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your encreaſe of felicity to your dying day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt zealous deuoted humble Seruant.
<hi>Humphrey King.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:4"/>
            <head>To all his Honourable Friends, or Honeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed
Wel-wiſhers whereſo-euer.</head>
            <p>IT would well become a deuote <hi>Hermite</hi> to begin with
<hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> vnto you, but that I hold friuolous, ſince
if you want <hi>Grace,</hi> go by <hi>Ieronimo,</hi> you are no friends for me:
and if you be not men of <hi>Peace,</hi> it is not my <hi>Hermites</hi> Staffe,
and my little bucker-clapdiſh, that will appeaſe you, wherefore
<hi>Shokkatorum,</hi> that which will bee ſhall bee. If you will bee quiet
and leaue your mocking tongue you may, if not, floute on by leaue, the more
ſport it breeds you, the gladder I am (as the <hi>Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſaies)
that I haue it for you. Cunning Lawyers, vpon the falſe miſtaking of a
<hi>T.</hi> or an <hi>N.</hi> or putting in a daſh ouer-plus (if the Debtor
bee rich and able roundly to fee them) will make a Writ of Error of any thing:
doe not ſo by mee I beſeech you, for I am a very bad writer of
<hi>Orthography,</hi> and can ſcarce ſpell my <hi>Abcie</hi> if it were
laid before mee. The <hi>Printer</hi> may helpe mee to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to you true
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> but as I am a true man to God and the King, hee findes it
not in my Coppy. I meane well, that I am ſure, and if I had better meanes to
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, I would make you better vnderſtand it: in the meane time, what
is but meane, take it in as good part, as if it were the higheſt treble that
the cleereſt Poetical war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling throate could ſhrill or quauer forth.
Dangerous miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreting I feare not, 
<q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9765:4"/> 
                  <l>Since <hi>Enuy,</hi> that blacke venom'd To ad ſwolne
Elfe,</l> 
                  <l>Nere ſlanders a cleere conſcience to it
ſelfe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Onely if you could a little diſpence here and there with a hard
Rime or two, (in which yet you ſhall not ſay but there is ſome reaſon)
and my verſes that are like Cheaters falſe Dice of high-men and low-men,
one while eights, now tennes, another while foure-teenes, and ſometimes
ſixes, I will number you, (though I keepe no numbers) in the fore-moſt
ranke of my benefactors and fauourers. Me thinks a King by birth as I am,
ſhould not debaſe himſelfe to intreate ſo much. And yet I remember an
old ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyes game of <hi>King by your leaue</hi> (euer ſince I was a
boy my ſelfe) and ſo I am afraid you will cry, <hi>King by your leaue, we
are to haue about with you, beare it off with the head and ſhoulders how you
can.</hi> But if you do, vpon all the Cannes and quart-pots about
<hi>London</hi> I will be ſworne, (all Wine-pots from this generall rule
excepted, for them I haue for-ſworne till <hi>Michelmas,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
the new wine of <hi>Peru,</hi> that is made of no <hi>Grape,</hi> but a
ſtrange fruite in the <hi>VVeſt-indies,</hi> and is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to
the braine and the ſtomacke, then any reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or cordiall
whatſoeuer) vpon them I ſay I will abiure and renounce, all claime or
intereſt I haue had in that wicked word of <hi>Poetry,</hi> and bind my
ſelfe and my heires, neuer more to be publicans and ſinners, (or ſinners
in publique) in that vnfortunate Art of <hi>Printing.</hi> It hath bene told
mee, that thoſe that are ſlaine with the <hi>Indians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9765:5"/>poyſoned arrowes, die with their mouthes ſhut, and how the Butchers
in <hi>Germany,</hi> kill their ſheep after the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame order, by
tying a cord about their mouthes, and ſo ſtrangling them, that their
fleſh may be more ſwolne and puft vp: ſo would I die, by my good will, if
this my labour miſ-carry, and haue my mouth cloſed vp from euer ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
or writing hence-forward. Had I had learning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, I would haue framed an
inuectiue againſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe, I know, none ſaue the learned will
finde fault with me: but ſeeing I haue it not, I muſt heere end my
Epiſtle, and deſire ſuch as deſcend to deepely into my
ſhallowneſſe, no otherwiſe to eſteeme of my writings then of Drummes
and Trumpets in warre: which are not vſed ſo much to ſtir vp men to fury,
as to teach them to march in meaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you conceite me, HVMPHREY
KING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:5"/>
            <l>HOW dares the Author paſſe vnto the Preſſe,</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Satyres, Eſſayes, Epigrams</hi> do ſwarme,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Comicke,</hi> and the ſtately <hi>Tragicke</hi>
verſe,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Caltha</hi> metamorphos'd with a charme?</l>
            <l>A ſtrong imagination wrought this thing,</l>
            <l>His name being <hi>King,</hi> he thinkes himſelfe a King.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>In diſcommendation of the Author.</head>
            <l>IT is no Tale, the Hermite is beli'd,</l>
            <l>The Author ouer-aw'd, or much beguild.</l>
            <l>Time paſt ſpoke plaine, and did no vices hide,</l>
            <l>Time preſent muſt be pleaſed like a child.</l>
            <l>Chriſten thy booke anew, then do'ſt thou well,</l>
            <l>And call it Truth, a Tale's an Infidell.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>
               <hi>KIng</hi> neuer prou'd more King in any thing,</l>
            <l>Then in this plaine-ſong, freedome of a King:</l>
            <l>Plaine vnaffected ſtile, yet vices ſting;</l>
            <l>Why <hi>(King)</hi> I ſee y faith thoul't needs be King.</l>
            <trailer>Conueniunt rebus nomina ſaepe ſuis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>TO grace the man whom all the Graces fauour,</l>
               <l>Lies not within the compaſſe of my quill,</l>
               <l>Suffice it his moſt plauſible behauiour,</l>
               <l>Drawes all the happy choiſe of wits, and skill,</l>
               <l>To loue, admire, affect, and dignifie,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, and theſe his labours pleaſing lines.</l>
               <l>Mongſt whom my zeale preſumes to ſignifie</l>
               <l>Some loue to him, in whom ſuch vertue ſhines.</l>
               <l>An <hi>Hermits Tale,</hi> an <hi>Hermits Heart</hi>
declareth;</l>
               <l>Sincere the one, ſo ſpotleſſe pure the other,</l>
               <l>That with the vertues euermore it ſhareth,</l>
               <l>By no meanes ſuffering ill the good to ſmother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go then ſweet <hi>Hermits Tale,</hi> and tell the
wiſeſt,</l>
               <l>Perfection liues not ſtill in the preciſeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incor, non vinco.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>THat I haue lou'd, and moſt reſpected thee,</l>
               <l>True-honeſt <hi>Humphrey:</hi> I do heere proteſt,</l>
               <l>And that the world ſhall witneſſe it with me,</l>
               <l>Embrace this ſigne of loue amongſt the reſt;</l>
               <l>Wilt thou haue more? my word I will engage:</l>
               <l>Nay further yet: Il'e take a ſolemne oath,</l>
               <l>By the Red-herring thy true Patronage,</l>
               <l>And famous <hi>Naſh,</hi> ſo deere vnto vs both:</l>
               <l>By all the Bowers that we haue reueld in,</l>
               <l>Our merry times, that gallop hence ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>By all the houres we haue together bin,</l>
               <l>By all our vowes of friendſhip that haue paſt:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By theſe I ſweare my loue, and thy worke graced,</l>
               <l>On her rich worth, and honour'd Titles placed.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9765:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>LAtely the Muſes from their forked hill</l>
               <l>Deſcending downe into our humbler vale,</l>
               <l>To taſte the fruits of Induſtrie and Skill</l>
               <l>In makers of this time: Beheld thy <hi>Tale.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which, though it did appeare emptie of Art,</l>
               <l>(As that thy modeſtie hath ſtill profeſt)</l>
               <l>Yet this faire cenſure they did all impart:</l>
               <l>Thy loue to Arts therein was well expreſt.</l>
               <l>But when they ſaw to whom it was deſign'd,</l>
               <l>(A Ladie of her graces; ſo inſpir'd</l>
               <l>With euery bountie both of forme and mind,</l>
               <l>As of the Muſes ſelues, ſhe is admir'd)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They vow'd, thy worke ſhould liue; and with one voyce,</l>
               <l>Approu'd thy Iudgement in ſo ſweet a choyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Suus cuique mos.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9765:7"/>
            <head>AN Halfe-peny-worth of Wit, in a Peny-worth of Paper. ALIAS.
¶The Hermites Tale.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <l>VVAlking by a Forreſt ſide,</l>
               <l>An ancient Hermite I eſpide,</l>
               <l>White was his head, old was his face,</l>
               <l>Pale were his lookes, obſcure his place,</l>
               <l>And in his hand I might behold</l>
               <l>A booke all torne and very old;</l>
               <l>I willing both to ſee and know</l>
               <l>His place, and why he liued ſo,</l>
               <l>Went to ſalute him, as vnknowne,</l>
               <l>To be a partner of his moane,</l>
               <l>He being of an humble ſpirit,</l>
               <l>As one that heauen would inherite,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9765:8"/>A friendly welcome to me gaue,</l>
               <l>And brought me to his homely Caue,</l>
               <l>VVhere he had liu'd full twenty yeares,</l>
               <l>And for his ſinnes ſhed many teares;</l>
               <l>Thinking euery howre to die,</l>
               <l>Knowing the worlds vnconſtancie.</l>
               <l>Then ſate he downe, and to me told:</l>
               <l>I once was yong, but now am old,</l>
               <l>And welcome is mine age to mee,</l>
               <l>That no more changes I may ſee;</l>
               <l>For I haue ſeene from time to time,</l>
               <l>The higheſt fall, the loweſt clime:</l>
               <l>Contray to that we expect,</l>
               <l>To make vs know the worlds defect,</l>
               <l>How time and death doth ſtill preſage</l>
               <l>The fickleneſſe of euery age</l>
               <l>Like to the Moone that hath no power,</l>
               <l>Louing to change, both day and howre.</l>
               <l>Vnhappy men that liue therein,</l>
               <l>VVhere nought is found but death and ſin.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9765:8"/>Then gentle youth, if you would know</l>
               <l>Heauens delight, the world forgoe,</l>
               <l>For wordlings, very ſeldome can</l>
               <l>Two Maiſters ſerue, both God and man.</l>
               <l>For if a man your Maiſter bee,</l>
               <l>You then muſt ſinne as well as hee,</l>
               <l>To ſmooth his taſte, and pleaſe his vaine,</l>
               <l>How much ſo ere the ſinne containe.</l>
               <l>If he a Tyrant do profeſſe,</l>
               <l>Then muſt his ſeruant be no leſſe;</l>
               <l>Or if an Athieſt hee bee knowne,</l>
               <l>So muſt you be, or elſe be gone:</l>
               <l>For I haue heard a prouerbe old,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be rul'd by him that hath the gold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such are the errours of our age,</l>
               <l>VVhen ſoules for gold are laid to gage:</l>
               <l>A ſubſtance that wiſe men beſot,</l>
               <l>A pleaſure full of paine, God wot.</l>
               <l>VVhen I was yong, as you are now,</l>
               <l>I ſpent my youth, I know not how,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9765:9"/>Rating my pleaſure at ſuch a price,</l>
               <l>More worth, then Heauens Paradice.</l>
               <l>Theſe worldly pleaſures are but toies</l>
               <l>Vnto the high celeſtiall ioyes,</l>
               <l>Where God doth ſit on Syon hill</l>
               <l>To giue the doome of good and ill,</l>
               <l>Then if you knew how ſweete it is</l>
               <l>To meditate on heauens bliſſe,</l>
               <l>You ſure would leaue all worldly ſtrife</l>
               <l>And liue with me, an Hermites life.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Anſwere.</head>
               <l>FAther or friend, what ere you bee,</l>
               <l>A happy man you ſeeme to mee,</l>
               <l>The happieſt man this day on earth,</l>
               <l>Bleſt in your age, and at your birth;</l>
               <l>Whoſe heauenly words my heart hath wonne,</l>
               <l>To liue with you, and be your ſonne:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9765:9"/>Leauing the world, too full of woes,</l>
               <l>VVhere ſinnes and errors daily flowes,</l>
               <l>And take me to your homely Cell,</l>
               <l>VVhere ſweet content doth euer dwell;</l>
               <l>Then if you pleaſe to take the paine,</l>
               <l>For Chriſtes ſake, a ſoule to gaine,</l>
               <l>Your counſell graue on me beſtow,</l>
               <l>That true religion I may know:</l>
               <l>For all Kings Chriſtned are at warres</l>
               <l>For Conſcience, and religious iarres;</l>
               <l>And controuerſies now haue made</l>
               <l>One King on other to inuade,</l>
               <l>VVith warre, with death, and famiſhment,</l>
               <l>Each other ſtill they do torment;</l>
               <l>VVith Chriſtians bloud they die the ground,</l>
               <l>Piercing ſweet babes with many a wound,</l>
               <l>And aged men with ſiluer'd haires,</l>
               <l>There groueling lie, in blood and teares;</l>
               <l>VVhat ſinne, what death, ſo-ere befall,</l>
               <l>They make Religion cauſe of all.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9765:10"/>A grieuous thing, when they ſhall come</l>
               <l>To giue account for all and ſome</l>
               <l>Before that God that knowes their thought,</l>
               <l>If they for true Religion fought:</l>
               <l>Or whether for ambitious pride</l>
               <l>They meant Religion to deuide;</l>
               <l>And ſo to kindle Gods diſpleaſure</l>
               <l>For Kingdomes, Crownes, and worldly Treaſure;</l>
               <l>Knowing them all to be illuſions,</l>
               <l>To bring our ſoules into confuſions,</l>
               <l>And make vs wiſh, ere we haue done,</l>
               <l>Such warres had neuer beene begun.</l>
               <l>Where Chriſtians ſeeke each others blood,</l>
               <l>Their meaning ſeldome can be good.</l>
               <l>But if our warres were like to them</l>
               <l>Which were before <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Againſt the Turkes, which there abod,</l>
               <l>Sworne enemies vnto our God,</l>
               <l>VVhat happy men then had we bin,</l>
               <l>So to haue dy'd, and cleer'd our ſin?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:9765:10"/>VVhereas (God wot) we now do goe</l>
               <l>To ſeate our Brothers ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>Alas! if they in warres that die,</l>
               <l>Did not confeſſe a Trinitie:</l>
               <l>Or if that Heathen men they were,</l>
               <l>VVithout all knowledge, faith or feare</l>
               <l>Of Chriſt that dy'd to ſaue mankind</l>
               <l>From death and hell, to him aſſign'd;</l>
               <l>Then without any offence at all,</l>
               <l>They might take pleaſure in our fall.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hermite.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY ſonne of warres you haue complain'd,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is a plague for ſinne ordain'd;</l>
                  <l>A plague that God himſelfe hath choſe,</l>
                  <l>His wrath and iuſtice to diſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>And for my part, I muſt confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Our ſinnes (my ſonne) deſerue no leſſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9765:11"/>Chriſt knowes we haue deſerued more</l>
                  <l>Then euer our fathers did before:</l>
                  <l>And yet we ſay, they neuer knew</l>
                  <l>VVhere true Religion euer grew.</l>
                  <l>For they were ſtill inſtructed then</l>
                  <l>By Friers and Monks, old ancient men,</l>
                  <l>Such as did then attribute all</l>
                  <l>Vnto Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> not to <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Saying that Chriſt had choſe alone,</l>
                  <l>Him for the Rocke, and corner ſtone,</l>
                  <l>And vnto him the keyes reſign'd,</l>
                  <l>To open, ſhut, to looſe and binde.</l>
                  <l>Taking the word as it was ſpoken,</l>
                  <l>And not the ſence it did betoken:</l>
                  <l>And ſo by <hi>Peters</hi> ſuperioritie,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> doth chalenge his authoritie.</l>
                  <l>But come my ſonne, time doth vs call.</l>
                  <l>Wee'l leaue our Chriſt to iudge of all.</l>
                  <l>And go with me, Il'e teach thee how to ſpend</l>
                  <l>The Sommer day in ſolace with thy friend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9765:11"/>Where thou ſhalt ſee the pleaſure of
this wood,</l>
                  <l>Exceeds all other, were they nere ſo good.</l>
                  <l>Heere dwels poore men that neuer vſe to ſweare,</l>
                  <l>But yea and nay, and by the weedes they weare.</l>
                  <l>Farre be it from them to wrong his holy Name</l>
                  <l>That gaue them life, and leaue to vſe the ſame.</l>
                  <l>To him they call; and ſtill for mercy crie,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they know in iuſtice all muſt die;</l>
                  <l>They liue ſecure, and free from any ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>And thinke <hi>Content</hi> to be the ſweeteſt life:</l>
                  <l>And ſo it is, to ſuch poore men as theſe,</l>
                  <l>That looke for nought, but how their God to pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>See how they labour all day till they ſweate,</l>
                  <l>And take great paines, and all to get them meate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sauing your Tale, good Father, what be thoſe,</l>
                  <l>That in their lookes decipher many woes,</l>
                  <l>And many times they ſeeme to make a ſhow</l>
                  <l>As though fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they came, they faine wold go,</l>
                  <l>Impatient of the croſſes God hath ſent</l>
                  <l>Them for their good, becauſe they ſhould repent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9765:12"/>Well ſaid (my ſonne) thy iudgement I
commend,</l>
                  <l>For Man hath croſſes to none other end,</l>
                  <l>And he is happieſt that can ſuffer any</l>
                  <l>For his ſake, that for vs hath ſuffred many.</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou not heard a ſong of <hi>Phillida,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Herpilus,</hi> and eke <hi>Coren?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>why theſe, my ſonne, be they.</l>
                  <l>The one is <hi>Coren,</hi> that once tooke</l>
                  <l>delight his Hawkes to lure,</l>
                  <l>Th'other <hi>Herpilus,</hi> (poore man)</l>
                  <l>that all paine did endure</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Phillida,</hi> and that is ſhee,</l>
                  <l>which oft did flowers twine,</l>
                  <l>And Garlands make of Violets,</l>
                  <l>to pleaſe her <hi>Corens</hi> mind.</l>
                  <l>But he regarded not her loue,</l>
                  <l>nor when ſhe frownd or ſmild</l>
                  <l>It mou'd not him, he neuer car'd,</l>
                  <l>for once he was beguild.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9765:12"/>And yet ſhee was the faireſt Maide</l>
                  <l>that euer nature fram'd,</l>
                  <l>And all the Shepheards would reioyce</l>
                  <l>when <hi>Phillida</hi> was nam'd.</l>
                  <l>But Time, the enemie to Youth,</l>
                  <l>ſent Sickeneſſe, Beauties croſſe,</l>
                  <l>As meſſenger, to tell her now</l>
                  <l>ſhee is not as ſhee was:</l>
                  <l>Her golden haire, her for-head ſmooth</l>
                  <l>her quicke full ſpeaking eie,</l>
                  <l>Her comely noſe, her lips</l>
                  <l>where loue did banquet royally,</l>
                  <l>Haue chang'd their hue, for what can laſt,</l>
                  <l>or hold that will away?</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Iudas</hi> fatall Elder-tree,</l>
                  <l>ſo lookes poore <hi>Phillida.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her haire with Daffadillies dight</l>
                  <l>Ewreth'd with purple-ſilke,</l>
                  <l>Is now within a night-cap tide,</l>
                  <l>vnkemb'd, as white as milke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9765:13"/>Her fore-head all with furrowes fild</l>
                  <l>that was ſo ſmoth and white,</l>
                  <l>Her eies (the Cabinets of loue)</l>
                  <l>haue loſt their wonted ſight;</l>
                  <l>Her noſe is ſharpe, her iawes are falne,</l>
                  <l>her lips that were ſo red,</l>
                  <l>Now lookes like Siluer-ore vntried,</l>
                  <l>and no teeth in her head.</l>
                  <l>Ah ſonne, if they in Court that liue</l>
                  <l>did once but thinke of this,</l>
                  <l>They ſoone would finde amongſt themſelues</l>
                  <l>how they had done amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>In pampring vp their filthy fleſh</l>
                  <l>which is a ſlaue to time,</l>
                  <l>An enemy vnto the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>a maſſe of filth and ſlime.</l>
                  <l>But come my ſon, we'le now go home</l>
                  <l>vnto our homely Caue,</l>
                  <l>And leaue poore <hi>Phillida</hi> to mourne</l>
                  <l>that wiſheth for her graue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:9765:13"/>For <hi>Herpilus,</hi> and eke
<hi>Coren,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>of whom the Muſes ſong,</l>
                  <l>They vow'd to die with <hi>Phillida,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>becauſe they lou'd ſo long.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Father, I neuer heard a Tale</l>
                  <l>to moue a man to ruth,</l>
                  <l>And make him thinke of all his ſinnes</l>
                  <l>committed in his youth</l>
                  <l>As this which you haue told;</l>
                  <l>A terror vnto thoſe</l>
                  <l>Which in their beauty, wit, or ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>do confidence repoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is no terror (ſonne) to thoſe</l>
                  <l>which meane not to repent,</l>
                  <l>They neuer thinke of crooked age,</l>
                  <l>nor of their youth miſpent;</l>
                  <l>But head-long runne from ſin to ſin,</l>
                  <l>like ſheepe that go aſtray,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:9765:14"/>Yet now and then for faſhion ſake</l>
                  <l>they make a ſhow to pray;</l>
                  <l>And come to Church, and knocke and kneele,</l>
                  <l>becauſe they may be taken</l>
                  <l>For honeſt, good, and godly men,</l>
                  <l>that haue the world forſaken.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true Sir, I haue heard of thoſe</l>
                  <l>that vnder ſhew of zeale;</l>
                  <l>Would hate the time, &amp; curſe the ſtate,</l>
                  <l>and at the Clergy raile;</l>
                  <l>Ill minded men, enuious, and proud,</l>
                  <l>diſcentious, full of wroth,</l>
                  <l>Monſtrous diſſemblers, fild with ſin,</l>
                  <l>in whom there is no troth;</l>
                  <l>Theſe zealous men, meane to erect</l>
                  <l>a Church, ere it be long,</l>
                  <l>Where Papiſt neuer ſet his foote,</l>
                  <l>nor neuer Dirge was ſong;</l>
                  <l>Meane while, for feare their faction breake,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9765:14"/>they thinke it beſt behoues them,</l>
                  <l>To meete in Barnes, and there to Preach,</l>
                  <l>euen as the Spirit moues them,</l>
                  <l>And there they pray, before they Preach,</l>
                  <l>in heart, with one accord,</l>
                  <l>That they may neuer laugh, for feare</l>
                  <l>they do offend the Lord;</l>
                  <l>Then ſtarteth vp a brother ſtraight</l>
                  <l>vpon a wicker Chayre,</l>
                  <l>And talkes of ſinne, and how it raignes</l>
                  <l>amongſt vs euery where;</l>
                  <l>How euery ſtate is diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>How many ſinne, how few repent:</l>
                  <l>What May-poles, and what Whitſon-ales,</l>
                  <l>What ringing, and what old-wiues tales,</l>
                  <l>Are now beleeu'd to be the way</l>
                  <l>To ſaue vs all another day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſon, theſe men will nere endure the touch,</l>
                  <l>They know too little, and they ſpeake too much,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9765:15"/>Their lookes are ſmoth, like Siluer
purifide,</l>
                  <l>They will proue Copper, when they ſhall be tri'd.</l>
                  <l>I neuer heard of theſe which ſeeme ſo pure,</l>
                  <l>Which for Chriſts ſake wold Martirdom endure,</l>
                  <l>And yet no doubt, as long as peace remaines,</l>
                  <l>Their conſcience will endure any paines.</l>
                  <l>But if the God of warre abroad ſhould range,</l>
                  <l>And catch theſe men that long to ſee a change,</l>
                  <l>You then ſhould ſee them all within one day,</l>
                  <l>For very feare of death, to turne Turke-way.</l>
                  <l>But come my ſonne, ſit downe and let vs eate</l>
                  <l>Theſe homely cates, in ſteed of better meate,</l>
                  <l>And leaue theſe men that enuy ſo the ſtate,</l>
                  <l>To die like dogs, that can do nought but prate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'le tell you, Father, of a Tale</l>
                  <l>that is in <hi>Skeltons</hi> rime,</l>
                  <l>A fooliſh Tale, but yet a Tale</l>
                  <l>to driue away the time;</l>
                  <l>Of a very pleaſant lad</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9765:15"/>my Tale I muſt beginne,</l>
                  <l>That came into a houſe, by chaunce,</l>
                  <l>where Sectaries did Inne,</l>
                  <l>And being in their company,</l>
                  <l>not knowing what they were,</l>
                  <l>He was as merry as a Pie,</l>
                  <l>ſtill skypping here and there,</l>
                  <l>Till at the laſt a ciuill Sire</l>
                  <l>came mildly towards him,</l>
                  <l>And like a man of God, rebuk'd</l>
                  <l>this yong-man for his ſinne.</l>
                  <l>This merry Lad, mus'd at the man,</l>
                  <l>as one loath to offend,</l>
                  <l>Saying, if he had done amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>he would be glad to mend.</l>
                  <l>Night drew on, Supper came in,</l>
                  <l>they all with one conſent</l>
                  <l>Deſir'd this yong-mans company,</l>
                  <l>and he was well content.</l>
                  <l>He ſadly ſate all Supper while,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:9765:16"/>and not a word he ſaid:</l>
                  <l>And as they did, ſo would he do.</l>
                  <l>They after ſupper prayed,</l>
                  <l>And Chapters read, and ſung a Pſalme</l>
                  <l>all to inſtruct the youth,</l>
                  <l>What great delight he ought to haue</l>
                  <l>in reading of the truth.</l>
                  <l>VVhen that the Lord was ſerued thus,</l>
                  <l>they cald a reckning preſently,</l>
                  <l>And would not let this yong man pay,</l>
                  <l>but thank'd him for his company.</l>
                  <l>This pleaſant Lad muz'd at the men,</l>
                  <l>yet being farre from ſcorning,</l>
                  <l>Intreated them to breake their faſt</l>
                  <l>with him the next day morning.</l>
                  <l>They thank'd him all with one conſent,</l>
                  <l>but eſpecially Maiſter <hi>Powes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſired him to beſtow no coſt,</l>
                  <l>but onely Beefe and Browes.</l>
                  <l>You ſhall haue nothing eſe (quoth he)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9765:16"/>welcome ſhall be your chiefe,</l>
                  <l>And ſo good-night, vntill we meete</l>
                  <l>all at a peece of biefe,</l>
                  <l>The morning came, &amp; there they met,</l>
                  <l>the boy that knew his time,</l>
                  <l>Set them downe to breakefaſt ſtraight,</l>
                  <l>and then began his rime.</l>
                  <l>You are welcome heartily, vnto luſty <hi>Humphrey,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVelcome here muſt be your chiefe</l>
                  <l>To a friendly peece of Biefe,</l>
                  <l>Such as was vs'd in ancient time</l>
                  <l>VVhen houſe-keeping was in prime;</l>
                  <l>VVhen the Biefe and Brewes flouriſht,</l>
                  <l>VVhen the ſilly ſoules were nouriſht,</l>
                  <l>Then 'twas a wonder to the poore</l>
                  <l>To ſee a Porter keepe the doore,</l>
                  <l>Then were ſilly harmeleſſe folkes,</l>
                  <l>Plaine chimneyes then were full of ſmoakes:</l>
                  <l>Euery table then was ſpred,</l>
                  <l>And furniſht out with Biefe and bread,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9765:17"/>Euery man then tooke a pleaſure</l>
                  <l>In his houſe to ſpend his treaſure.</l>
                  <l>Who was then the Gentries Gueſt?</l>
                  <l>The Widdow poore, that's oft oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>The Souldiers with their wounds and skarres</l>
                  <l>Bleeding for their Countries warres.</l>
                  <l>Then in the Country dwelt true pitty,</l>
                  <l>Now Chriſtmas is but for the Citty;</l>
                  <l>A Gentleman of ſmall reuenew,</l>
                  <l>Had then the poore for his retinew.</l>
                  <l>Waſt not then a merry time</l>
                  <l>When thy neighbour came to mine,</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou lend me twenty pound</l>
                  <l>For to buy a peece of ground?</l>
                  <l>Without ſtatute, or a bond</l>
                  <l>Their word as good as any hand.</l>
                  <l>Then men of ancient calling</l>
                  <l>Loued no pride for feare of falling,</l>
                  <l>Country Ruſſet was their wearing,</l>
                  <l>And Kendall greene, for feare of tearing.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9765:17"/>The Clothier ſcarce the Mercer knew,</l>
                  <l>Now Silke-wormes make the Sheepe to rue,</l>
                  <l>The Plough-man liu'd, ſweete was his paine,</l>
                  <l>The Taylor now ſweepes vp his gaine.</l>
                  <l>If any now do take compaſſion,</l>
                  <l>'Tis to checke the oldeſt faſhion;</l>
                  <l>Yet paying for new faſhions gold,</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of all, the new is old.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what meane I to runne ſo farre?</l>
                  <l>My fooliſh words may breed a skarre,</l>
                  <l>Let vs talke of <hi>Robin Hoode,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And little <hi>Iohn</hi> in merry Shirewood,</l>
                  <l>Of Poet <hi>Skelton</hi> with his pen,</l>
                  <l>And many other merry men,</l>
                  <l>Of May-game Lords, and Sommer Queenes,</l>
                  <l>With Milke-maides, dancing o're the Greenes,</l>
                  <l>Of merry <hi>Tarlton</hi> in our time,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe conceite was very fine,</l>
                  <l>Whom Death hath wounded with his Dart,</l>
                  <l>That lou'd a May-pole with his heart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9765:18"/>His humour was to pleaſe all them</l>
                  <l>That ſeeme no Gods, but mortall men,</l>
                  <l>For (ſaith he) in theſe our daies,</l>
                  <l>The Cobler now his Laſt downe laies,</l>
                  <l>And if he can but reade, (God wot)</l>
                  <l>Hee talkes and prates he knowes not what,</l>
                  <l>Of May-poles, and of merriments</l>
                  <l>That haue no ſpot of ill pretence.</l>
                  <l>But I wonder now and then,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the wiſe and learned men,</l>
                  <l>VVith countenance grim, and many a frowne</l>
                  <l>Cries, Maiſters, plucke the May-pole downe.</l>
                  <l>To heare this newes, the Milke-maide cries,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the ſight, the Plough-man dies.</l>
                  <l>'Tis a ieſt to ſee when they beginne</l>
                  <l>For to plucke downe ſuch wodden ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Fooliſh men, and faith-leſſe too,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill profeſſe, and nothing do.</l>
                  <l>The Sectaries were in a rage,</l>
                  <l>and knew not what to ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9765:18"/>They ſpit, and chafd, and ſtampt
amaine,</l>
                  <l>and would haue gone away.</l>
                  <l>This merry Lad began to laugh,</l>
                  <l>and to them thus replide,</l>
                  <l>You ſee it ſtands not with my youth</l>
                  <l>from pleaſure to be tide,</l>
                  <l>I loue to ſit and laugh,</l>
                  <l>not to offend the wiſe,</l>
                  <l>I care not for their company</l>
                  <l>that honeſt mirth deſpiſe:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that be Saints abroad,</l>
                  <l>whoſe ſubſtance ſhadowes bee,</l>
                  <l>Let them go ſeeke Preciſian-ſects,</l>
                  <l>they are no mates for mee.</l>
                  <l>And when you are at home,</l>
                  <l>thinke of this prouerbe told,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Tree is ſtill knowne by his fruite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>if it be nere ſo old.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The poore men went away,</l>
                  <l>all diſcontent in minde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9765:19"/>And had no pleaſure to their meate,</l>
                  <l>but left it all behind.</l>
                  <l>Now, Father, be you iudge</l>
                  <l>who plaid the better part,</l>
                  <l>They with their zeale, or elſe the boy</l>
                  <l>that ſpoke with all his heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ſadneſſe my good ſonne,</l>
                  <l>I neuer yet did heare,</l>
                  <l>A Tale to that effect,</l>
                  <l>ſo much to pleaſe mine eare;</l>
                  <l>My iudgement I will ſtay,</l>
                  <l>vntill our better leiſure,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſhow thee heere a booke my ſonne,</l>
                  <l>wherein thou maiſt take pleaſure:</l>
                  <l>Heere ſhalt thou reade my ſonne</l>
                  <l>a volume of diſpaire,</l>
                  <l>The death of many a conquering king,</l>
                  <l>their liues, and what they were,</l>
                  <l>The wiſedome of this world,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:9765:19"/>the frailty of our age,</l>
                  <l>Our preſent time now acting ſinne</l>
                  <l>like Players on a ſtage.</l>
                  <l>I writ it with this hand</l>
                  <l>that once could guide a pen,</l>
                  <l>And ſet my Launce into my reſt</l>
                  <l>as well as other men.</l>
                  <l>But (oh) thoſe daies are paſt,</l>
                  <l>and now I wiſh to haue</l>
                  <l>For all my ſeruice done,</l>
                  <l>a white ſheete and a graue.</l>
                  <l>My Caske of ſteele is to a night-cap turn'd,</l>
                  <l>My ſhining Armour to a gowne of gray,</l>
                  <l>My youthful heart, which once with beauty burn'd</l>
                  <l>Like dreames illuſions, vading paſſe away,</l>
                  <l>Euen as the night doth from the glorious day.</l>
                  <l>My Naples Courſer is a banke of earth,</l>
                  <l>Whereon I ſit to manage all my ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>Twixt life and death, which are borne mortall twinnes.</l>
                  <l>My bridle now muſt be my Beades,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9765:20"/>The golden boſſes bookes,</l>
                  <l>And all my Sonnets muſt be prayers</l>
                  <l>VVhereon deuotion lookes,</l>
                  <l>My Launce turn'd to a Palmers ſtaffe</l>
                  <l>VVhich once was painted braue,</l>
                  <l>And all my followers be my ſinnes,</l>
                  <l>To bring me to my graue.</l>
                  <l>The ſhield which now my Page</l>
                  <l>Vnto my Prince muſt giue,</l>
                  <l>Is (time miſpent) <hi>An aged man.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>that can no longer liue.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beleeue me ſonne, I would not liue</l>
                  <l>For to be yong againe,</l>
                  <l>To be great Emperor of the world</l>
                  <l>The world I ſo diſdaine.</l>
                  <l>Iudge you if I ſay true,</l>
                  <l>Reade this, and know my mind,</l>
                  <l>They that haue eyes, may ſee the world,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe they are borne blind:</l>
                  <l>It is a world of care,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9765:20"/>The greateſt Prince that raignes</l>
                  <l>Hath not halfe pleaſure in his Crowne</l>
                  <l>To equall all his paines.</l>
                  <l>And he that liues in Court,</l>
                  <l>And can but fauour win,</l>
                  <l>VVhat ere he was, he may be ſure</l>
                  <l>That all will follow him.</l>
                  <l>The ſurly Vſhers then</l>
                  <l>VVill do him any grace,</l>
                  <l>That told him but a weeke before</l>
                  <l>He did not know his place;</l>
                  <l>His fellowes of the Guard,</l>
                  <l>VVhen he comes to the dore,</l>
                  <l>VVill all ſtand vp and make a legge,</l>
                  <l>That would ſit downe before.</l>
                  <l>But if this man be proud,</l>
                  <l>And full of high diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>Caring for nothing elſe at all</l>
                  <l>But for his priuate gaine.</l>
                  <l>Then Enuy mou'd in heart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9765:21"/>A Iury ſtraight doth call,</l>
                  <l>Inditing that vſurping man</l>
                  <l>Conſpiring his downe-fall.</l>
                  <l>And ſtraight he doth informe</l>
                  <l>The Iury what he was,</l>
                  <l>That now vſurpes, and hates the poore</l>
                  <l>And doth his betters croſſe.</l>
                  <l>The Poet hearing this,</l>
                  <l>Puls forth a booke of Tables,</l>
                  <l>And makes a ſubtill rime,</l>
                  <l>Much like to <hi>Eſops</hi> fables;</l>
                  <l>Then being fore-man, tels a Tale</l>
                  <l>That was not much regarded,</l>
                  <l>How men of vertue and of worth,</l>
                  <l>Did wander vnrewarded:</l>
                  <l>So he that liues in Court,</l>
                  <l>And doth not ſeeke to haue</l>
                  <l>The loue of euery priuate man,</l>
                  <l>And of the pooreſt ſlaue,</l>
                  <l>Let him be ſure of this,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9765:21"/>If Fortune chance to frowne,</l>
                  <l>Enuy in time will turne the wheele</l>
                  <l>And throw him head-long downe.</l>
                  <l>Who would bee ſuch a man</l>
                  <l>When Time his fortune reades,</l>
                  <l>That he muſt leaue his Offices,</l>
                  <l>And take him to his beades,</l>
                  <l>And in a ſhirt of hayre,</l>
                  <l>Repent his time miſled,</l>
                  <l>And giue his treaſure to the poore,</l>
                  <l>Whom hee hath iniured.</l>
                  <l>This were the way to go</l>
                  <l>In peace vnto his graue,</l>
                  <l>For none without they do repent,</l>
                  <l>Can any mercy haue.</l>
                  <l>But liues there ſuch a man?</l>
                  <l>No ſure there can be none,</l>
                  <l>We all are Lambes, no Foxes now,</l>
                  <l>The deuil's dead and gone,</l>
                  <l>No ſure: if he were dead,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9765:22"/>The Poets then would leaue</l>
                  <l>To write of thoſe that follow him,</l>
                  <l>And all the world deceiue.</l>
                  <l>But fare-well to the world</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe I come by ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>It neuer cares to grace ſuch men</l>
                  <l>As want both wit and wealth.</l>
                  <l>I cannot kiſſe my hand</l>
                  <l>Nor lout below the knee,</l>
                  <l>Nor take a feather from your gowne,</l>
                  <l>You know ſuch men there be.</l>
                  <l>In world one vndermines</l>
                  <l>another to no end,</l>
                  <l>And worſt they ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>who moſt in hope do ſpend,</l>
                  <l>Enuide they are,</l>
                  <l>on whom but Fortune ſmiles,</l>
                  <l>Though thoſe ſmiles turne</l>
                  <l>to nothing other-whiles.</l>
                  <l>The mighty, ſeeking</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9765:22"/>to enlarge their might,</l>
                  <l>Into contempt oft tumble</l>
                  <l>downe out-right.</l>
                  <l>The Lawyers Clyent</l>
                  <l>crouching on his knees,</l>
                  <l>Preuaileth nought,</l>
                  <l>except he bring large fees.</l>
                  <l>The Cittizen, the Scholler,</l>
                  <l>and the Boore,</l>
                  <l>Without a largeſſe,</l>
                  <l>are thruſt out of doore.</l>
                  <l>Brauery, the gallant nouice</l>
                  <l>thinkes doth all,</l>
                  <l>When it conſum'd,</l>
                  <l>his credite is but ſmall.</l>
                  <l>Valour and Wit,</l>
                  <l>proud on their tip-toes ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And thinke chiefe dignities</l>
                  <l>they may command.</l>
                  <l>When that a foole,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9765:23"/>a Paraſite, a Pander,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt them ſteps,</l>
                  <l>and they are ſet to wander.</l>
                  <l>So from the head</l>
                  <l>vnto the foote it fares,</l>
                  <l>Each one ſupplanteth</l>
                  <l>other vnawares.</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt builders,</l>
                  <l>againſt after ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>Fiſhing for honour,</l>
                  <l>baite their hookes with wormes;</l>
                  <l>Wormes that do dig</l>
                  <l>and delue for them all day,</l>
                  <l>Yet to all rauenous birds</l>
                  <l>are left a pray.</l>
                  <l>In Common-wealth</l>
                  <l>how many vainely dreame</l>
                  <l>Of Indian Mines,</l>
                  <l>that fiſh againſt the ſtreame?</l>
                  <l>How many, that but hauing</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:9765:23"/>one good bite,</l>
                  <l>A nodde, or leaſt glaunce</l>
                  <l>from their Miſtres ſight,</l>
                  <l>Coſt vpon coſt, clap thicke</l>
                  <l>and three-fold on,</l>
                  <l>And neuer ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>till they be quite vndone.</l>
                  <l>How many that do fiſh before the Net,</l>
                  <l>VVho offices before they fall do get,</l>
                  <l>And count all fiſh into their Net doth chaunce,</l>
                  <l>VVhom nought ſo vile, but ſerueth to aduance.</l>
                  <l>All theſe purſuing gaine, not true content,</l>
                  <l>Fiſh for their bane, their toile is fruitleſſe
ſpent.</l>
                  <l>This is the world my ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Then now ſome comfort giue</l>
                  <l>To me poore man, my time is come</l>
                  <l>I can no longer liue</l>
                  <l>Mine age, my bleſſed age,</l>
                  <l>VVherein I do reioyce,</l>
                  <l>Hath lent me time for to repent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9765:24"/>And ſing with Angels voyce,</l>
                  <l>Hymnes, Anthems, Laude, and Praiſe</l>
                  <l>Vnto the King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Which out of this vilde wretched world</l>
                  <l>Poore ſoules to heauen brings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You Poets all and ſome</l>
                  <l>That write of <hi>Eſops</hi> fables,</l>
                  <l>Conceiting plots to pleaſe the world</l>
                  <l>Notes from your booke of Tables;</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes that <hi>A-iax</hi> ſhould you call,</l>
                  <l>To make waſt-paper of you all</l>
                  <l>That ſpend your time to pleaſe the time,</l>
                  <l>With fictions, tales, and idle rime,</l>
                  <l>Leauing the marke that ſhould be hit,</l>
                  <l>To praiſe Gods glory, and your wit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> was erected</l>
                  <l>For Vertue, not for vice protected.</l>
                  <l>Ah, ſonne, I faint, mine age and I</l>
                  <l>Are ſtriuing now who firſt ſhould die:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:9765:24"/>My will is made, I haue no wealth,</l>
                  <l>But wiſhes, prayers, content, and health,</l>
                  <l>To thee my ſonne, and all my friends</l>
                  <l>That credite to this vaine world lends.</l>
                  <l>My ſwolne-ſicke heart, with death is toſt,</l>
                  <l>Like to a foote-ball in a froſt;</l>
                  <l>God bleſſe thee ſonne, now cloſe mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>I hope my ſoule to heauen flies.</l>
                  <l>And thus I end my Hermites Tale</l>
                  <l>Which is of mickle ruth,</l>
                  <l>It proues there is no hope in age,</l>
                  <l>Nor certainty in youth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As for this homely Tale,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And hee that made the ſame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath neither learning, wealth, nor wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſcarce can write his name.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
